Guide to the Harriett Joan Ehrlich Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Harriett Joan Ehrlich Papers
1967-2007
1990-2005
02/2008-005
Ehrlich, Harriet Joan
4.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The contents of this collection comprise the life of Harriet Joan Ehrlich. The bulk of the materials contained within revolve around Ehrlich’s tenure with the EEOC, specifically as director. The collection has been divided into eight (8) series: Correspondence, Certificates, Personal Writings, Multimedia, News Clippings, Press Books, In-Service Educational Materials, and Ephemera.
Biographical Information:
Harriet Joan Ehrlich was born in New Brunswick, New Jersey on February 12, 1935. She attended Syracuse University where she received a bachelor’s degree in home economics and started her career as a bridal consultant for Bloomingdales Department store. Ehrlich spent her younger years making a name for herself in the civil rights movement before joining the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) in Houston. While working as a director of a state enforcement unit in Philadelphia, Ehrlich pushed the local school district to resolve unequal pay for female janitors.
Over the next 24 years, Ehrlich worked tirelessly for the EEOC, becoming director of the Houston office and later the office in San Francisco. She actively spoke to the press, pushed EEOC lawyers to file more and larger cases, and reached out to civil rights leaders, clergy and business leaders. Even while bed ridden Ehrlich continued her work in labor advocacy, convening her staff in a San Francisco hospital room. Ehrlich died of leukemia at the age of 72.
Source:
Houston Chronicle, http://www.chron.com/news/houston-deaths/article/H-Joan-Ehrlich-longtime-worker-advocate-dies-1776151.php
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Awards; Correspondence; Ephemera; Photographs; Publications (document genre)
Personal Name:
Ehrlich, Harriet Joan
Topical Term:
Affirmative action programs -- Law and legislation -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- Law and legislation -- United States; United States. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The contents of this collection comprise the life of Harriet Joan Ehrlich. The bulk of the materials contained within revolve around Ehrlich’s tenure with the EEOC, specifically as director. The collection has been divided into eight (8) series: Correspondence, Certificates, Personal Writings, Multimedia, News Clippings, Press Books, In-Service Educational Materials, and Ephemera.
Detailed List of Contents
- Correspondence, id143245
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence to and from Ehrlich. The bulk of the material contained within pertains to EEOC business and issues. Sub-Series 2 consists of thank you notes from a wide array of individuals.
  - General, id143254
    - General Correspondence, 1967-1980; id143257 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1981-1984; id143258 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 1985-1987; id143259 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1988-1990; id143260 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1991-1994; id143261 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 1995-1997; id143262 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 1998-2000; id143263 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Thank You Notes, id143255
    - Thank You Notes, undated; id143265 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Thank You Notes, 1967-1988; id143266 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thank You Notes, 1990-1995; id143267 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Thank You Notes, 1996-2000; id143268 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Certificates, id143247
  The series consists of awards received by Ehrlich. Included are certificates of appreciation, resolutions and various other commendations. All materials in this series are in paper form.
  - 1979-1989, id143270 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1990-1999, undated, id143271 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Personal Writings, id143248
  This series contains the personal writings of Ehrlich. Included are appointment books as well as an original poem written by Ehrlich.
  - Daybooks, id143273 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Twas the Week After Christmas" Poem, undated; id143274 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Calvin Botley's Lecture Series, id143275 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Multimedia, id143249
  This series consists of audio visual materials. Of special interest is a photograph of Ehrlich receiving an award from Vice-President Al Gore.
  - Photographs, id143277 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - VHS "Teens Take on Sexual Harassment", 2004; id143278 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- News Clippings, id143250
  This series includes news clippings related to the EEOC or issues pertaining to the organization.
  - 1981-1989, id143280 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1989, id143281 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1990, id143282 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1991, id143283 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1991, id143284 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1992, id143285 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2000-2006, id143286 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Press Books, id143251
  This series consists of binders containing press releases and news clippings revolving around the EEOC or issues pertaining to the organization.
  - 1980s, id143289 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - 2005, id143290 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - 2005, id143291 (Box 2, Item 3)
  - January-May 2006, id143292 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - April-June 2006, id143293 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - July-December 2006, id143294 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - 2006-2007, id143295 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - January–December 2007, id143296 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - 2007, id143297 (Box 3, Item 5)
- In-Service Educational Material, id143252
  This series contains training materials provided by the EEOC. Included are reports and conference materials.
  - EEOC Annual Report, 2002; id143299 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Weekly Reports, September-December 2002; id143300 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Weekly Reports, January-April 2003; id143301 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Weekly Reports, May-June 2003; id143302 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - EEOC Internal Affairs, id143303 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Negotiation Workshop-Harvard Law School, 2001; id143304 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Negotiation Workshop Binder-Harvard Law School, 2001; id143305 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Guidance for EEOC, id143306 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Court Cases, id143307 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Published Materials, 1989, 1991, 1996, 2002; id143308 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Published Materials, undated; id143309 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reports and Papers, id143310 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Ephemera, id143253
  This series consists of two plaques honoring her service as director of the Houston branch of the EEOC.This series contains training materials provided by the EEOC. Included are reports and conference materials.
  - Farewell Plaques, 2003; id143312 (Box 4, Folder 13)